A Guide to the James Rex Riley Papers, 1971-1983: SC 0181
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
James Rex Riley Papers,
1971-1983
Special Collections, James Madison University
Riley, James Rex, 1938-1987
SC 0181
2.03 cubic feet; 5 boxes
This collection contains five boxes. The bulk of the collection consists of manuscripts of Dr. Riley's compositions and recordings of performances of his works.
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Audio recordings are not accessible pending reformatting. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
These materials, most of which had been in Dr. Riley's office at the time of his death, were donated to the Music Department by his widow, Susan Riley.
Bio/Historical Note
James Rex Riley was born in Shreveport, Louisiana in 1938. He graduated from Centenary College, then studied composition with Samuel Adler and Hunter Johnson at North Texas State University and the University of Texas at Austin, where he earned his doctorate. He taught at the University of Texas, Mississippi State University and Wichita State University, and came to James Madison University in September 1981. He won a number of prizes, including three ASCAP awards, and received commissions from such organizations as the San Antonio Chamber Music Society as well as James Madison University. He died March 29, 1987, after several years of struggling against a brain tumor.
Scope and Content
This collection contains five boxes. The bulk of the collection consists of manuscripts of Dr. Riley's compositions and recordings of performances of his works.
Index Terms
Subjects:
James Madison University. Music Dept
- Dedicatory Hymn and Fuguing Tune James Riley, Concerto #4 - Handel, Prelude and Allegro - W. Piston, May 6, 1978 (Box 1)
- Concert Music for Winds & Percussion James Riley, Cincinnati Conservatory Wind Ensemble, Robert Rustowicz, Conductor, May 27, 1977 (Box 1)
- Mississippi State University, Department of Music Education presents a Faculty Recital of compositions by James Rex Riley, February 11, 1970 (Box 1)
- James Riley, Concert Music for Winds and Percussion, Cincinnati Conservatory Wind Ensemble, R. Rustowicz, Cincinnati, Ohio, May 27, 1977 (Box 1)
- James Riley, Concert Music for Winds & Percussion, UTSA Wind Ensemble, Rustowicz, April 15, 1981 (Box 1)
- Riley - concert Music for Winds & Percussion, March 17, 1981 (Box 1)
- James Riley, Four Essays for Brass Quintet, Recorded by: San Antonio Symphony Brass Quintet, 1981 (Box 1)
- JMU Contemporary Music Festival, Virginia Composers, 1982 (Box 1)
- James Riley, Stick Games, ISU Percussion Ensemble, undated (Box 1)
- James Riley, Tangents, Tape Part, undated (Box 1)
- Riley, Textures for Trombone & Piano, April 19, 1974 (Box 1)
- Jazz Improvisation Class (play-a-long), undated (Box 1)
- Riley - TV Music, undated (Box 1)
- Two Choruses from Five Satirical Madrigals, James Riley, WSU Chamber Singers, April 19, 1971 (Box 1)
- James Riley, Visiones, March 15, 1975 (Box 2)
- Woodwind Quintet - James Riley, April 2, 1974 (Box 2)
- JMU Alma Mater, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Scope and Content
  Notes by Dr. Riley & various scores.
- Published compositions, 1973-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Conversation piece for trumpet, Tenuto, 1983. Dialogue for trumpet and percussion, Elkan-Vogel, 1974. Three acts for five trombones, Brass Press, 1973. Stick games, Southern Music, 1980. Visiones, Southern Music, 1976.
- Personal, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Includes a resume, copy of the funeral program, and clippings.
- Large manuscripts, undated (Box OV 1)
  Most are originals; a few are photocopies in files. Titles are: Celebration for band Sun-song; Concert music for winds & percussion; Superstar (folder); Masquerade (folder); Three songs for the day; Spheres (folder); String of pearls (folder); Tropical latitudes (folder); Valley ayres (3 copies)
- Small manuscripts, undated (Box OV 2)
  Most are originals; a few are photocopies in files. Titles are: Dedicatory hymn and fuguing tune Preludes & fugues (folder); Devil's dirge Sassy Sam (folder); Four scenes for orchestra (3 cop.); Second string quartet; Gemini (folder); Third string quartet (3 cop.); Pastime (2 copies)
- Performances of Dr. Riley's compositions, 1971-1983 (Box OV 3)
  18 5 inch reel to reel tapes of performances of Dr. Riley's compositions: Concert music for winds and percussion, WSU Wind Ensemble, 1975; Concert music for winds and percussion, Cincinnati Conservatory Wind Ensemble, 1977; Conversation piece, solo - Charles Bergine, 1979, 3 copies; Dedicatory hymn and fuguing tune, 1978, 2 copies; Dialogue, WSU, 1972; Four scenes for orchestra, WSU, 1973, 2 copies; Pastime. San Antonio Symphony Woodwind Quintet, 2 copies; Pirouettes, 1 copy 1982, 1 copy 1983; Second string quartet, WSU, 1974; Stick games, ISU Percussion Ensemble; Third string quartet, Concord Quartet, 1977; Textures, 1971.
  20 cassette tapes, of which some are Dr. Riley's work, others are by various composers, and some are commercial orchestras for classroom use; and Dr. Riley's card file of items in his files.